{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "One faction of fans of this sport supposedly promoted the heresy of Monophysitism, opposing pro-Orthodoxy fans. Supporters of this sport burned half of Constantinople during the reign of Justinian the Great in the Nika Revolt. The richest athlete in this sport, Gaius Appuleius Diocles, competed for the Reds using a quadriga. For ten points, name this sport held in the Byzantine Hippodrome and the Roman Circus Maximus, a highly dangerous vehicular race.",
      "answer": "chariot racing ”race” not needed after mentioned"
    },
    {
      "question": "This woman convened the first meeting of the Ninety-Nines. This woman’s spouse debunked baseless rumors that this person was secretly Tokyo Rose. Will Rogers facetiously coined the term “Powder Puff Derby” to describe a race where this pilot took third. The USGS Itasca failed to locate this person after she didn’t check-in with Howland Island. Fred Noonan disappeared with, for ten points, what American aviator, the first woman to fly solo across the Atlantic Ocean?",
      "answer": "Amelia Earhart"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country’s 1997 civil war partly grew out of riots after much of the population fell for Ponzi schemes promising 100% interest. The Sigurimi operated in this country under the orders of Communist dictator Enver Hoxha [HOE-jah] who declared the “first and only” Atheist state. In 1939, an Italian invasion of this country forced its King Zog to flee south to neighboring Greece. For ten points, name this Muslim-majority country in Eastern Europe with capital at Tirane.",
      "answer": "Albania"
    },
    {
      "question": "Businesses selling this good were attacked by the hatchet-wielding Carrie Nation. Frances Willard founded an organization which opposed the legalization of this good. The WCTU opposed the use of this substance which was the subject of the Volstead Act. The 18th Amendment banned the consumption of this substance until it was reversed with the 21st Amendment. For ten points, name this intoxicating substance that was illegal during Prohibition.",
      "answer": [
        "alcohol",
        "equivalents and more specific answers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "With the help of Cossack K.S. Leontiev, this kingdom’s military modernized in the 1890s and entered a dispute with a European power over the wording of the Treaty of Wuchale. This country, which was once controlled by the communist Derg regime, fought a 17-year civil war that ended in 1991 with it losing its access to the Red Sea. Eritrea broke away from, for ten points, what East African country that is also blocked from the sea by Djibouti and Somalia?",
      "answer": [
        "Ethiopia",
        "Abyssinia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During a siege in this conflict, the victorious commander allegedly remarked “we have passed” in response to a speech by Dolores Ibarruri. A so-called Fifth Column of sympathetic civilians aided attackers during a battle won by Emile Mola in this war. The Carlists and Falangists were united during this conflict to defeat the Republicans. Francisco Franco won, for ten points, what conflict that included the Siege of Madrid?",
      "answer": "Spanish Civil War"
    },
    {
      "question": "A genre of music developed in this city was originally called “la-la” and was pioneered by Clifton Chenier, “The King of Zydeco.” A band leader from this city headed the Red Hot Peppers and composed the “King Porter Stomp.” The Original Dixieland Jass Band pioneered traditional jazz in this city, which was also home to a trumpeter who recorded “West End Blues” and “What a Wonderful World.” “Jelly Roll” Morton and Louis Armstrong hailed from, for ten points, what city where musicians parade down Bourbon Street during Mardi Gras?",
      "answer": "New Orleans"
    },
    {
      "question": "The South African Police Service murdered 17 strikers who extracted this commodity in the Marikana Massacre. Great Zimbabwe merchants often traded this commodity for porcelain and silk with the Sultanate of Kilwa. A colony named for this commodity first fell to a European power after multiple Anglo-Ashanti Wars. For ten points, name this commodity that, along with salt, was the primary trade good of medieval and early modern West Africa.",
      "answer": "gold"
    },
    {
      "question": "Robert Nozick has advocated for a “watchman” type of this entity, which he details in a book that pairs this entity with Anarchy and Utopia. According to Max Weber [VAY-ber], this entity has a monopoly on the legitimate use of force. When these entities coincide with a particular ethnicity, they are called the “nation” type. For ten points, give this term that describes certain governmental entities as well as divisions of the USA like Vermont and Hawaii.",
      "answer": "states"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this man’s presidency, John Fries organized a rebellion by the Pennsylvanian Dutch. This President signed a set of four laws that increased his power to deport French immigrants and that criminalized anti-government libel, the Alien and Sedition Acts. The “Midnight Judges” were appointed by this man to promote Federalist interests in the court system shortly before leaving office. Thomas Jefferson succeeded, for ten points, what 2nd President of the United States?",
      "answer": "John Adams"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A story about this man claims he was impersonated by his wife Pompeia Plotina. During the reign of this man, Lusius Quietus ended the Kitos revolt. This man commissioned Apollodorus of Damascus to create a bridge over the Danube. This man’s victory at Tapae, and thus his conquest of Dacia, are commemorated in a spiral bas relief located upon a namesake column in the Forum. For ten points, name this second of the Five Good Emperors.",
        "answer": "Trajan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Trajan was succeeded by this man who ordered the construction of a wall to separate Roman Britain from the Picts.",
        "answer": "Hadrian"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This Regionalist work was inspired by the artist’s visit to the town of Eldon, Iowa and titled for a style of architecture that appears in the farmhouse in the background. The central figures in this painting were modeled by the artist’s dentist and sister, who was irritated when this painting was originally exhibited as “an Iowa farmer and his wife.” For ten points, name this Grant Wood double portrait of a stoic pitchfork-holding farmer and his unamused daughter.",
        "answer": "American Gothic"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "American Gothic was awarded third prize in a competition held by this midwestern city’s Art Institute, which then purchased the painting for its collection.",
        "answer": "Art Institute of Chicago"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Francis Parkman examined this route in a work subtitled Sketches of Prairie and Rocky-Mountain Life. Jedediah Smith, one of the early fur trappers to map this route, discovered its South Pass. Other routes such as the Bozeman Trail followed the eastern half of this route. Travelers along this route rode in Conestoga wagons to the Willamette Valley. For ten points, name this route used by the settlers of a namesake northwestern state.",
        "answer": "Oregon Trail"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Most settlers travelling the Oregon Trail started out in Independence, a town in this state.",
        "answer": "Missouri"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Tourists to this town can read a historic inscription about its founding on Egg Rock and walk a replica of the Old North Bridge. According to a “Hymn” named for this town, “Here once the embattled farmers stood, / And fired the shot heard round the world.” For ten points, name this Massachusetts town that, with Lexington, was the site of the opening clashes of the American Revolution.",
        "answer": "Concord"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "“Concord Hymn” was written by this American poet and transcendentalist, a friend of Henry David Thoreau.",
        "answer": "Ralph Waldo Emerson"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Martin Garcia Onez de Loyola led an expedition to capture the last emperor of these people, Tupac Amaru. Legendarily, a ruler of this empire came out of Pacaritambo holding a golden staff after being birthed from the divine pairing of Mama Killa and Inti. This empire that used the knot system of quipu experienced a civil war between Huascar and Atahualpa. For ten points, name this South American empire conquered by the conquistador Francisco Pizarro.",
        "answer": "Incan Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This capital city of the Incan Empire is home to the Coricancha temple. Pachacuti built the empire from this city.",
        "answer": "Cuzco"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Despite the outcome of this battle, the Maypenny Commission still seized control of “Paha Sapa.” Mitch Bouyer, a scout hired by the United States Crow Agency, died during this battle. After attacking a village filled with women and children, forces under Marcus Reno were isolated from the rest of this battle. Sitting Bull and Crazy Horse led the winning forces at, for ten points, what 1876 battle, the last stand of George Custer?",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of the Little Bighorn [",
          "Custer’s Last Stand before it is read",
          "Battle of Greasy Grass"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "“Paha Sapa” is the Lakota word for this rugged region of South Dakota, and parts of Wyoming, that experienced a gold rush in the 1870s.",
        "answer": "Black Hills"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "When syncretized with the Egyptian god Amun, this Roman deity was depicted with ram horns. The Flamen Dialis was the high priest of this deity, who formed the Archaic Triad with Quirinus and Mars. In the Metamorphoses, this deity transforms into an eagle to kidnap the Phrygian prince Ganymede; in the form of a bull, this god kidnapped Europa. This son of Saturn was the husband of Juno and the father of Minerva. For ten points, name this chief Roman god, the Roman equivalent of Zeus.",
        "answer": [
          "Jupiter",
          "Jove"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Metamorphoses was written by this Roman poet, who was exiled to the Black Sea city of Tomis by Augustus Caesar in 8 AD.",
        "answer": "Ovid or Publius Ovidius Naso"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country’s constitution, the Henrician Articles, defined the rights of its elected kings. The Union of Krewo was a precursor to this country created when a Jagiellon ascended the throne. In this country, any member of its legislature could veto a bill through Liberum veto. Prussia, Austria, and Russia partitioned this country three times. The Union of Lublin created, for ten points, what country governed from Krakow and Vilnius?",
        "answer": "Poland-Lithuania"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Poland-Lithuania participated in this early 18th century war in which a Russia-led coalition curbed the growing power of Sweden.",
        "answer": "Great Northern War"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Mexican-American War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "State whose border with Mexico was set along the Rio Grande after the war.",
          "answer": "Texas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Future Confederate President who fought in the war.",
          "answer": "Jefferson Davis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Democratic President who led the United States during the war.",
          "answer": "James K. Polk"
        },
        {
          "question": "1848 treaty that ended the war.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Resolution called for by Abraham Lincoln that demanded to know where American blood was spilled.",
          "answer": "Spot Resolutions"
        },
        {
          "question": "Never-passed bill that would have banned slavery in territory acquired during the war.",
          "answer": "Wilmot Proviso"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battalion composed of Irish-Americans that fought for the Mexican Army.",
          "answer": "Saint Patrick’s Battalion"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Alexander the Great",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Kingdom he ruled in northern Greece.",
          "answer": "Macedonia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Previous king, his father, who was assassinated in 336 BC.",
          "answer": "Philip II of Macedon"
        },
        {
          "question": "City, destroyed by Mount Vesuvius, where a mosaic of him was found.",
          "answer": "Pompeii"
        },
        {
          "question": "333 BC battle where he defeated Darius III, two years before Darius” ultimate defeat at Gaugamela.",
          "answer": "Battle of Issus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Beloved horse who he supposedly tamed by hiding his shadow.",
          "answer": "Bucephalus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle where that horse died near a namesake river in India.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Hydaspes River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Phoenician island city where he constructed a causeway to allow an attack.",
          "answer": "Tyre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Collective name for his generals, who fought several wars to divide his empire.",
          "answer": "Diadochi"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Australia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that colonized it as a penal colony.",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland",
            "UK",
            "Great Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City ceremoniously built by King O’Malley contained in the Federal Capital Territory.",
          "answer": "Canberra"
        },
        {
          "question": "Vast, remote area explored by the Afghan Cameleers that comprises most of Australia’s interior.",
          "answer": "outback"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country with which it formed the ANZAC Corps.",
          "answer": "New Zealand"
        },
        {
          "question": "Flightless bird that “won” a “war” against Australian wildlife management in 1932.",
          "answer": "emus"
        },
        {
          "question": "First female Prime Minister of Australia, a Labor politician who led from 2010-2013.",
          "answer": "Julia Gillard"
        },
        {
          "question": "1854 rebellion started by gold miners in Ballarat.",
          "answer": "Eureka Stockade or Eureka Rebellion"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime Minister who mysteriously disappeared while swimming in 1967.",
          "answer": "Harold Holt"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Leroy Gore ran a front-page editorial calling for the recall of this man after he disrespected Ralph Zwicker. In an election against Robert La Follete Jr. this man said “Congress needs a (20 pts)",
        "tail-gunner.” This man orchestrated his own political downfall when he organized a series of 1954 hearings investigating the army. In a speech in (10 pts)",
        "Wheeling, West Virginia, this man claimed to have a list of 205 names of workers in the State Department. For ten points, name this Wisconsin senator who started a 1950s witch hunt for hidden Communists."
      ],
      "answer": "Joseph McCarthy"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A member of this family sent the adviser Drouyn to resolve the Luxembourg dispute with (20 pts)",
        "Prussia. In 1864, a member of this family overthrew the government of Benito Juarez to place the Hapsburg (10 pts)",
        "Maximillian I on the throne of Mexico. Another member of this family seized control of Spain, sparking the Peninsular War. For ten points, name this family that had two Emperors of France, both named Napoleon."
      ],
      "answer": "Bonaparte"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man declared that “peaceable secession” was impossible and that he was not a “Northern man, but an American” in the Seventh of March speech. During a debate with Robert (20 pts)",
        "Hayne, this man declared “Liberty and Union, now and forever, one and inseparable.” This man helped resolve the Maine boundary dispute after signing a (10 pts)",
        "treaty with Great Britain’s Ashburton. For ten points, name this member of the Great Triumvirate, a politician from Massachusetts."
      ],
      "answer": "Daniel Webster"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) John Love and John Sawhill were informally called “czars” of this concept, reflecting their influence on American policy in the 1970s. The Nuclear Regulatory Commission joined a cabinet department for this concept established by (20 pts)",
        "Jimmy Carter in 1977; the department’s current Secretary is a former Presidential candidate who (10 pts)",
        "forgot that he wanted to eliminate the department in a 2011 debate, former Texas governor Rick Perry. For ten points, name this Cabinet department that includes the management of oil and natural gas production."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "energy",
        "energy czar",
        "Department of Energy",
        "Secretary of Energy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Private landlords in this country controversially maintained control over two-thirds of their land following an 1861 emancipation reform. This country was the home of the People’s (20 pts)",
        "Will, a revolutionary group that, in 1881, assassinated the leader of this country. This country ended its institution of (10 pts)",
        "serfdom in the aftermath of its loss in the Crimean War. For ten points, name this country where Tsar Alexander II was assassinated in St. Petersburg."
      ],
      "answer": "Russia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) With Roger Penrose, this figure names a set of theorems regarding gravitational singularities; with Leonard Susskind, this figure debated the black (20 pts)",
        "hole information paradox. This figure discussed the work of five other scientists in On the Shoulders of Giants. The (10 pts)",
        "radiation emitted by an evaporating black hole is named for this author of A Brief History of Time. For ten points, name this British physicist who suffered from ALS and died in 2018."
      ],
      "answer": "Stephen Hawking"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man authorized Operation Carlota to aid the MPLA in one conflict despite his country suffering the “Special Period.” During one conflict this man, and his (20 pts)",
        "26th of July Movement supporters, were forced to hide in the Sierra Maestra. Operation Mongoose was an effort to kill this man that included plans for an exploding (10 pts)",
        "cigar. This man noted that “history will absolve me” in defending his assault on the Moncada Barracks. Fulgenico Batista was overthrown by, for ten points, what longtime dictator of Cuba?"
      ],
      "answer": "Fidel Castro"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1907, riots were sparked in this city by nationalist outrage at the staging of John Millington Synge’s work Playboy of the Western World. James Connolly led this city’s namesake “lockout,” an (20 pts)",
        "anti-British labor dispute that lasted for six months in 1913. An armed insurrection in this city during (10 pts)",
        "World War I led to the death of sixty rebels in the Easter Rising. For ten points, name this headquarters of the political party Sinn Fein [shin fayn], the capital of Ireland."
      ],
      "answer": "Dublin"
    }
  ]
}